welcome to meditating with john verveigh
we're going to live stream today and
tomorrow uh tomorrow is going to be a
significant review
of philosophical contemplative
companionship
then we're going to switch to a weekly
schedule we will be meeting
every saturday at from 10 a.m to 11 a.m
eastern time the discord server
is going to continue to have its
meditation
meditation and contemplative practices i
believe they do two sits every day
uh they also do group lectio divina
they're going to house
and home uh the philosophical
contemplative companionships
there's excellent discussion so i'm
hoping that the sangha
will move there and find a new and
vibrant home there
we are going to have uh that first
lesson
uh from 10 a.m to 11 a.m on september
the 12th
the first of the new lessons will be on
september the 12th at 10 a.m eastern
time
at the end of every session as you know
there have been
uh q a we'll have one today we'll have
one tomorrow
please limit the questions at that time
to anything from the entire ecology of
practice whether it's from the eastern
traditions or the western traditions
there will also be of course significant
q a time on the saturday
meetings we should come up with a new
name for those we'll try and think of an
interesting and provocative one
if you have more general questions uh
you can bring those
uh to the live stream general q a uh
that's going to be
the third friday of this month which
is september the 18th um at 3 p.m
eastern time
if you're joining us for the first time
this is probably all very like strange
uh don't be put off by it please
note that we have actually done um like
110 classes as our 110th class
so there's a lot for you to learn
so please go to the description for this
video
take a look at the links for previous
lessons and sits do lesson one right
away
do uh i would recommend one or two
lessons every week
and then you'll catch up meet on the
discord server
the links are also um in the description
and you will be able to continue
learning this practice
learning the psychology practices i
should say as well as
being able to join this really wonderful
sangha
that has formed around uh this online
streaming course
all right so today uh it's just going to
be a regular day
uh we are going to begin with chanting
then we will go into silent sit uh we'll
have some time for some
questions and observations notifications
at the end
and then that will be it for today uh
reminder that tomorrow
will probably go a little bit longer uh
because i'm going to do a significant
review of the philosophical
contemplative companionships we'll have
the whiteboard up again and everything
we are experimenting today uh
with some new software and the two
cameras
which we'll we will be making use of
more extensively
tomorrow so please be patient with us as
we work out the bugs
when we get this working smoothly it
will definitely improve
uh the quality of the lessons that will
be given
on saturday all right everybody uh
please
come into your basic posture set your
phones on do not disturb
and we will begin together when i say
begin
one
one one
begin your silence it
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communitas
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so let's see if there's any questions
answer comments
it's just coming up now
so we have a
question from mark welcome as always
mark
how are contemplation and savoring
related are they the same
or do you overlap does one require there
are other specific practice
differences so
i think of contemplation and meditation
as basically attentional
where we're directing our attention and
contemplation is seeing through
where savoring has more to do
with um
opening up affectively with an a affect
right affectively opening up your
awareness
um so that there is
more uh coming in through sense
and more coming in so more coming in
through imagination
more coming in from imagination the
perception the pre-hending
more sight more insight etc
and so i suppose that
there could be savoring i hadn't thought
about this question i hadn't really put
it together
um taxonomically so that's why i'm going
through this carefully
i suppose though that savoring is
possible
both within meditation
because you can be opening up right
you're
making the flow of intelligibility
you're getting into the flow of
intelligibility more
and you could be doing that inwardly
directed in meditation
outwardly directed in contemplation
so i think savoring
is more basic practice in the sense
that it gets us into
a joy filled conformity
with the being with being and that and
that being of course can be
unfolding within in meditation and
without
in contemplation or with all
in prajna and so this
and that's why i think there is
traditionally a state of bliss
associated with the non-duality of
prajna and that would make sense given
what we're we're working through
together now because
the bliss would be not the savoring
of not meditative savoring or
contemplative savoring
but the savoring of non-duality sort of
pure being
pure savoring of pure being so that's
how i think i would try to
put those together i think more
reflection theoretical reflection
is needed on that um but
yeah i mean the problem with it is of
course is that attention and awareness
are bound and interpenetrate each other
within
consciousness um but yes
yeah uh annotation contemplation seem to
be
directional and that brings in attention
whereas savoring seems to be
awareness it seems to be sensitizing
and sensing the flow of intelligibility
victoria it's good to see you victoria
how do how often do i practice
pre-meditation malorium
um this is a stoic practice and we will
talk about when we get to lessons this
is the practice
of um
imagining and then we're going to talk
about the fact that stoicism
is not downward there's a lot of
imagination and there's a lot of the
imaginal
um and and we'll talk about imaginary
and imaginal again
in in depth uh within uh stoic practices
it's the practice of like when you
you're seeing your son
like let's say for me seeing my son
maybe kissing him good night saying
uh uh i may lose him tomorrow um i may
never see him again some people do more
specific version of the practice they
get an
object that they really like they spend
time with it they develop affection for
it and then they
uh break it um as a way and so what
you're doing is practicing
uh in countering so pre-meditation ahead
of time
you know thinking about but also
meditating upon ahead of time
loss um so i don't
do it that often in the sense of doing
it with specific
people but i do tend to do it
um daily and that i have
a reflection in which i consider the
fatality of all things
and i don't consider it just
intellectually i meditate on it i really
let it
resonate in in into me
how all things
have an
a permanent their existence isn't
permanent but they
as long as they exist there's an aspect
of them
that is forever independent from
my narratives my project uh the meanings
of my life so i do that
on a fairly regular basis pretty much
almost a daily basis
i found that seems to me
to be i i i think this is just a
personality difference so i'm not
recommending it in general
i think that version of the practice for
me seems to
it it seems to grab me more than the
individual ones that
tend to be emotionally startling
but they don't tend to to
orient me towards the general sense of
it um
but i can readily i readily acknowledge
that i could see it being completely
reversed for other people
that doing the more specific version of
the pre-meditation
could really be powerfully symbolic
of uh the fatality of all things at
large
so i hope that answered your question
victoria um
it made me reflect maybe i should go
back to the more specific practice more
regularly for a while
and and see give it a taste and a driver
again for a while
kiera kroger uh hi kyra observation
i i regularly have felt the experience
of contraction in my body and then i
mentally recoil from the contraction
during yoga today on discord i realized
that i can breathe into the contraction
like it would breathing into a stretch
in yoga that felt
insufficient that's very good so yoga of
course means ultimately to yoke
conjugal it's the off it's to be wedded
it's to be coupled
and if we can
do that if we can couple to body armor
in the way you're describing that's a
very powerful way
uh it's a very powerful way of
befriending yourself
of coming into a deeper wedding to
himself and i don't mean in the
narcissistic oh i'm so wonderful and
unique and special and the universe is
here just for me
and all that um what i mean
is you know that what we've been talking
about throughout the befriending of
oneself
so i carry a lot of body armor here
on the left side of my body some of it
has to do with
sort of uh historical psychodynamic
trauma
some of it has to do with the ongoing
sense that there is a part of my brain
that's hyper vigilant
about the uh the meniere's in my left
ear and of course i can't
ignore it because it's always ringing
there's always the pain and the pressure
uh and so moving
doing exactly we're talking about care
moving into that
that contraction and that resistance um
the way it rebounds and this is the
befriending the way it rebounds into
my psyche and discloses aspects of my
psyche and
opens me up um it's very hard to
put into sort of concrete terms but it's
a very powerful experience
it's like it's it goes from being uh
physical mental all right there's a
physical thing that has sort of a mental
aspect
to reverberating and being much more
mental and existential
and it's a very powerful experience so
i'm glad that you are getting a taste of
this
and i encourage you to continue to
pursue that
as a way of befriending yourself
alternate
hi alternate in meta-meditation i
include the whole of humanity
and the ecosystem it is inter-built with
this feeling of oneness seems at odds
with the concept
of countries and modern life uh
suggestion
that being at odds is is a good thing
so one thing to do is to step back and
embrace that
that there's a see
countries are extensions of egocentric
um orientation um you know my
country our country you know it's it's
it's it's that um and of course we need
countries et cetera
i'm not some sort of crypto anarchist at
least i don't think i am
um but when you get to the meta
and that all falls away and it's odd
what's what what's your what your
recognizing what you're recognizing
what's coming into awareness
is that that way of thinking
isn't actually part of the nature of
things the
countries and the divisions um and so
what seemed
natural and habitual and inevitable
is disclosed to being conventional
uh constructed and malleable that
doesn't mean it's
evil or illusory that's a mistake that
people too often leap to
oh because it's changeable and malleable
right it's therefore it's not real
um
so coming to the awareness
that that mode
isn't the same thing as the order of
things is a profound thing
so giving all of that is hopefully an
affordable context
savor the sense of the oddness meditate
into it
inquiring mindfulness unpack it let it
teach you
let it let it draw you let it deduce
from you
further realizations try to savor
the difference you know information is
the difference that makes a difference
savor that difference and how it is
transforming you
rainer ludwig thanks john for opening so
many new exciting doors for me
your teachings have enriched my life in
my retirement
and i'm looking forward to continuing
the journey of self-exploration with you
thank you rayner for sharing that and
thank you for your commitment and
encouragement
and thank you for reminding us that
there's a reframing happening here
where there's a there's going to be a
continuity of practice but we're
shifting
to a different way in which it unfolds
raha jonas question i captured myself
recently paraphrasing some facts while
sharing them
or adding some individual uniqueness to
them i promised myself in every practice
to be mindful of my speech
do you think this is enough for now to
deal with this
um you yeah definitely um
yeah remember don't hold yourself to
harsh perfectionism but to virtuous
friendship
um but yes i i think uh
setting the intent but perhaps setting
it through the day um
and sometimes it's good to pick one of
the promises and make that what you're
going to especially pay attention to
uh throughout the day um
but i think could be like celebrate that
so the the temptation uh when we note
these things is to ah
right but instead say oh great i'm
starting to do it
i'm starting to become more mindful of
my speech i'm starting to realize i'm
doing these things for a while
just be satisfied
take that cautiously be satisfied with
just catching it
and noticing it and then what will
happen is is that's
and just encourage it and wow this is
good and encourage it
and keep doing it and keep looking for
it and make it a
a pleasurable experience a learning
experience
not one that's reflecting on your
uh your character but one that is
reflecting on your growth
and and and then after you've gotten
a more reliable sense of being able to
catch that and witness it
then try to catch it earlier
like you know how we like when you're
doing inquiring mindfulness and you're
trying to
catch the earliest and earliest
inception of conception
right and and try and catch it earlier
and earlier increase your sensitivity
and then you get to a place where you've
caught it early enough
that you stare around it and it's not
this huge oh
no it's like
oh so that's my recommendation
uh for going forward on that deborah
wagstaff observation experience quite a
few solutions to struggle
in these silent minutes today that's
that's really wonderful
that's really wonderful um so this is
one of the ways in which
the your buddha nature is starting uh to
come forth
uh to to grow and to be born within you
and it's one of the ways in which you
can experience
befriending yourself so celebrate it and
thank you for sharing that
alexi simenov hello alexi it's good to
hear from you again
a question what is the right balance
between self-reflection meditation and
action
recently i enjoyed physical practices
and
scale sitting head practices i'm not
quite
um clear on
what the last thing is referring to but
i have a sense of what your question is
so they that so the the
um this is something i talked about in
the uh the series
awakening for the media crisis there's
the problem we we face two extremes that
we want to get away from
impulsivity in which we just act on
impulse
um velman calls this being a wanton
like like wanton behavior and frankfurt
uses a similar idea and the problem with
impulsivity is it works at cross
purposes it works against itself
and so we lose agency and so we practice
forms of reflection and meditation
and we withdraw from action into
contemplation
and what we get is we get some space and
some freedom
from that impulsivity and we start to be
able to
organize our impulses so that they are
not at cross purposes and
we reduce our inner conflict but you can
withdraw too much
in which you are the the
the reflection is upon reflect like you
can get to you
and development talks about like hamlet
as this
masterful work of art about a person who
is so reflecting upon his reflections of
his reflections
uh that he has disconnected himself
from the machinery of agency he so
uncoupled himself
that he can't get a momentum
of action going he becomes um withdrawn
the buddha
warned about a similar thing in which
people
use meditation as a form of spiritual
bypassing and we've talked about this
spiritual bypassing in which what
they're doing is it is is to escape
into kind of the contentedness of like a
cabbage
or or a clot of earth uh because
um they have so withdrawn
from the connection and so
the idea is right that we want
and and it's a oil i'll be a canadian
and i will find
the uh the average point the middle
point between them
and the problem is that's not right
either so what you need is a dynamical
uh constantly shifting you need
something that
brings with it the flexibility of
reflection
but the coupling contact
of impulsivity and this is where taoism
is
especially helpful although
stoicism and epicureanism can help us
out here as well
because taoism argues for
something between reactivity of the
wanton and the reflexivity of the hamlet
character
and so between reactivity and uh
over and too much reflexivity is what
they call spontaneity
so when you're when you're acting
spontaneously you have
awareness um you have a coherence
and you have a flexibility to your
action
but it is still engaged and coupled to
the world
um and spontaneity of course is a way
of activating and accentuating and
in some senses accelerating the flow
experience that we're all capable of
having
and part of what these practices are
doing in general this is not the only
thing they're doing
but part of what they are doing is
taking the flow experience
and increasing our cognitive flexibility
and our cognitive power such that the
scope and the depth of flow
opens up broadly stephen baxter in fact
argues
that he proposes that the buddha's
enlightenment
is to be comprehensively in a state of
flow
and this seems very similar to what the
taoist sages
are so what you're trying to do
is is uh toggle between
toggle your practices and you're right
they have a compensatory relationship to
each other
so you're constantly moving between
uh right the extremes of
automatic uh reflexivity and
and you know overly um active uh
i'm sorry reactivity and overactive
reflexivity
and so you're trying to steer between
them and get the optimal grip
and you're trying to get that and expand
that optimal grip
so that capacity to flow becomes more
and more um
a way of life and a way of being so i
hope that was helpful
and i look forward to more questions and
observations
uh tomorrow we will be going longer
tomorrow so please remember that
thank you everyone for joining i want to
thank you my
to my dear friend and uh techno mage
amar my beloved son jason they're doing
a lot behind the scenes making this
all work uh please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next video
please follow me on twitter for updates
about these streams
please point others to this series
in order to help them it's very
important
that if you can you join the discord
server so you can keep up
the daily meditative practice the
single most powerful predictor of you
continuing
with a course of growth and an ecology
of practice
is if you are in sanga if you are doing
it with other people
so please get on the discord server to
keep this
up find other discussion groups find the
yoga and other moving practices
the the group lectio divina and as
i said the the discord server is working
out how to home
uh philosophical contemplative
companionships which we will review
tomorrow
so please remember that continuity of
practice
is more important than your quantity of
practice don't hold yourself to the
standard
of a harsh perfectionism
but to a virtuous friendship because
there is no enemy
not harshness worse than your own mind
and body
but there is no friend no ally no true
contemplate not no true contemplative
companion
on the path better
than your own mind and body be lamps
unto yourselves
and to to each other take good care i'll
see you all tomorrow
you